American Council of Learned Societies. Committee on Native American Languages. 1882-1958 Mss.497.3.B63c
American Philosophical Society
American Council of Learned Societies Committee on Native American Languages, American Philosophical Society
1882-1958
Mss.497.3.B63c
American Philosophical Society
80.0 Linear feet
Formed in 1927 under the initiative of Franz Boas, Edward Sapir, and other academic linguists, the Committee on Native American Languages of the American Council of Learned Societies was charged with documenting the endangered languages of indigenous Americans. The Collection of the American Council of Learned Socities Committee of Native American Languages is one of the largest and most significant primary resources for study of the indigenous languages of North America. Beginning with the creation of the Committee in 1927, and periodically added to since by the APS, the collection has grown to over 80 linear feet of material representing at least 166 languages and dialects from the United States, Canada, and Mexico. The formats range from field notes and ethnographic texts to slip files, vocabularies, lexica, and grammars, and dozens of linguists and Native consultants are represented. Although most of the material was collected in the 1920s and 1930s, a signficant number of items have been added that extends the range of dates represented both backward and forward.
American Council of Learned Societies. Committee on Native American Languages.
African American History Note
There are at least two items in this collection which may be of interest to scholars of African American history:
Hurston, Zora Neale. " The Florida Expedition (#46)." n.d. 3 pages. Brief report by a student of Franz Boas on fieldwork in Florida studying African American folklore, story-telling, religion, and common-held beliefs. Hurston notes that "the bulk of the population now spends its leisure in motion picture theatres or with the phonograph and its blues."
King, Louis E. " Negro life in a rural community (#49)." Circa 1931. 166 pages. Anthropological dissertation study of African American life in a rural community during the years 1927-1931. The work is divided into several sections: Background, Family Life, Breadwinning and Shelter, Education, Activities of the Group, Leaving Home, and Comparing Life in Different Rural Communities.
Other Finding Aids note
Most of the materials in the ACLS collection, along with other materials on Native American languages, are indexed in the online Daythal Kendall Guide to Native American Collections at the American Philosophical Society.
Related Archival Materials note
The APS contains dozens of collections with material on Native American Languages, the majority of which are indexed in the online Daythal Kendall Guide to Native American Collections at the American Philosophical Society.
Separated Materials note
American Council of Learned Societies. Correspondence, 1926-1927. (506.73 Am72co)
This small but important collection of correspondence relates to the formation of the Committee on Research in the Native American Languages, its grants, and its publications. Correspondents include: Edward C. Armstrong, Leonard Bloomfield, Franz Boas, R. W. Bryan, James McKeen Cattell, Pliny Earle Goddard, Charles H. Haskins, J. W. Hewitt, Melville Jacobs, Roland G. Keat, Alfred L. Kroeber, Waldo G. Leland, Robert M. Lester, Fang-Kuei Li, Adrien G. Morice, William A. Oldfather, Gladys A. Reichard, Edward Sapir, E. H. Sturtevant, John R. Swanton, Walter F. Willcox. The collection is not calendared.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of American Council of Learned Societies, 1945.
Scope and Contents note
The Collection of the American Council of Learned Socities Committee of Native American Languages is one of the largest and most significant primary resources for study of the indigenous languages of North America. Beginning with the creation of the Committee in 1927, and periodically added to since by the APS, the collection has grown to over 80 linear feet of material representing at least 166 languages and dialects from the United States, Canada, and Mexico. The formats range from field notes and ethnographic texts to slip files, vocabularies, lexica, and grammars, and dozens of linguists and Native consultants are represented. Although most of the material was collected in the 1920s and 1930s, a signficant number of items have been added that extends the range of dates represented backward into the 1880s and forward in the late 1950s.
Includes notes and manuscripts of Franz Boas; materials solicited by and sent to Boas from field workers and native informants; manuscripts submitted for publication in the International Journal of American Linguistics (1917-1939); manuscripts resulting from research supported by the Committee on American Native Languages of the American Council of Learned Societies (1927-1937); papers of anthropologists and linguists associated with Boas and Edward Sapir; reports and other materials resulting from Phillips Fund grants made by the APS.
During the 1940s, the ACLS collection was arranged by language (and language family) by C. F. Voegelin and Zellig S. Harris, who also listed a significant quantity of miscellaneous non-linguistic material. Their index was published in a supplement to Language 21, 3 (1945). Among the non-linguistic material not indexed by Voegelin and Harris are data on folklore, mythology, and general ethnology, with some emphasis on African Americans, Africans, and the work of Boas's colleagues in Russia.
Since its arrival in Philadelphia, the APS has periodically added additional material to the collection. Among the more notable additions are some highly important field notes and other material donated by Alfred Kroeber in 1946 relating to early research (1902-1910) on California Athabascan languages (Chilula, Hupa, Kato, Mattole, Nongatl, Pomo, Sinkyoke, Tolowa, Wailaki, and Whilkut), and a suite of manuscripts by Edward Sapir presented by his family and colleagues in 1972. A number of individual linguists have also contributed individually to the collection, including Edward Ahenakew, Morris Swadesh, Kenneth Croft, Norman A. McQuown, Gordon Marsh, and C. F. Voegelin.
This finding aid is intended to parallel the online Daythal Kendall Guide to Native American Collections at the American Philosophical Society, with most entries culled verbatim. The materials in this finding aid are arranged according to language, dialect, cultural group, or region, and then by call number. When applicable, references to microfilm versions are included at the end of the entry.
Native American Images Note: Nearly 1,700 images of Northwest Coast Native Americans in linguistic notebooks collected from 1900-1940. Black and white silver gelatin photographs and sketch drawings by native consultants given to ethnologists Franz Boas, Edward Sapir, and Jaime de Angulo. Pencil sketches of clothing, utensils, musical instruments, decorative patterns, weapons, and totem figures of primarily Salish, Nootka, and Quileute tribes. Of particular interest, color pencil sketches of Bella Bella (Heiltsuk) masks. Numerous Nootka face paintings are also of note. In oversize, a linguistic map of the southern part of Hecate Strait, British Columbia, Canada. Most of the images are original with some photographs from the Anthropology Division of the Geological Survey of Canada. Note: Folders containing images are noted in the inventory.
Biographical/Historical note
Formed in 1927 under the initiative of Franz Boas, Edward Sapir, and other academic linguists, the Committee on Native American Languages of the American Council of Learned Societies was charged with documenting the endangered languages of indigenous Americans. Wielding grants to encourage research, the Committee was chaired by Boas and staffed by Manuel J. Andrade, Jaime de Angulo, Roland B. Dixon, Pliny E. Goddard, Bernard Haile, John P. Harrington, Harry Hoijer, Melville Jacobs, Diamond Jenness, Alfred V. Kidder, Alfred L. Kroeber, Truman Michelson, Frans M. Olbrechts, Gladys A. Reichard, Frank G. Speck, Edgar H. Sturtevant, Morris Swadesh, and John R. Swanton, among others.
Ahenakew, Edward; Andrade, Manuel José, 1885-1941; Angulo, Jaime de; Banister, John, Jr.; Beynon, William, 1888-1958; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942; Bogoras, Waldemar, 1865-1936; Chamberlain, Alexander F.; Deloria, Ella Cara; Dixon, Roland Burrage, 1875-1934; Freeland, L. S., (Lucy Shepard), 1890-1972; Geological Survey of Canada.; Goddard, Pliny Earle, 1869-1928; Gould, Marian K.; Harrington, John Peabody; Henry, Jules; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976; Hunt, George; Hurston, Zora Neale; Jenness, Diamond, 1886-1969; Jochelson, Waldemar, 1855-1937; Kalibala, Ernest B.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963; Kroeber, A. L., (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960; Lange, Gertrud, 1879-; Michelson, Truman, 1879-1938; Mukasa, Ham, 1871-1956; Olbrechts, Frans M., 1899-1958; Quain, Buell Halvor, 1912-1939; Reagan, Albert B.; Reichard, Gladys Amanda, 1893-1955; Roberts, Helen H., (Helen Heffron), 1888-1985; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950; Sturtevant, Edgar Howard, 1875-1952; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967; Swanton, John Reed, 1873-1958; Teit, James Alexander, 1864-1922; Warren, John; Achumawi language; African Americans--Florida; African Americans--Folklore; African Americans--West Virginia; Anthropology, ethnography, fieldwork; Athapascan languages; Atsugewi language; Autobiography; Bella Coola language; Benin--History; Chehalis language; Cherokee language; Chimakum language; Chinese language; Chiricahua language; Christianity--Africa; Chukchi--History; Clothing and dress--Middle East; Cree language; Culture, community, organizations; Cyanotypes; Dakota language; Dictionaries.; Ethnographic texts; Ethnology--Africa; Ethnology--Russia; Ethnology--United States; Face painting; Field notes.; Fijians--Social life and customs; Folk music--Puerto Rico; Folklore; Folklore--Africa; Folklore--British Columbia; Folklore--Florida; Folklore--Uganda; Group portraits; Haida language; Heiltsuk Indians; Hopi language; Hupa language; Indians of North America--Alaska; Indians of North America--British Columbia; Indians of North America--Languages; Inuktitut language; Jews, Ethiopian; Kalapuya language; Kalispel language; Kathlamet language; Kutenai language; Kwakiutl language; Laguna dialect; Lillooet language; Linguistics; Maps.; Mayan languages; Nahuatl language; Nass language; Navajo language; Nez Percé language; Nitinat language; Nootka Indians; Nootka language; Northwest Coast Indians; Ntlakyapamuk language; Photographs; Plantations; Pomo language; Quileute Indians; Quileute language; Religion, religious organizations; Salish Indians; Salishan languages; Shasta language; Sketches.; Slip files; Social conditions, social advocacy, social reform; Tarahumara language; Tarascan language; Tlingit language; Tolowa language; Tsimshian language; Tunica language; Twi (African people); United States -- Emigration and immigration.; Volga River Region (Russia)--History; Wailaki language; Watercolors; Winnebago language; Wintu language; Word lists; Yana language; Zapotec language
- Non-American and non-linguistic material
  - Autobiography of a native of Dahomey, West Africa, n.d.; AMs, 9pp. (incomplete); Unidentified
    Scope and Contents note
    Autobiographical manuscript of descendant of a Falasha Jew from Dahomey, including account of his return to Africa in 1910.
    Existence and Location of Copies note
    Microfilmed as: 372.7 reel 1
  - Bibliography on race, TMs, 88 slips; [Boas, Franz, 1858-1942](?)
    Microfilmed as: 372.7, reel 1
  - Folklore in British Columbia, n.d.; AMs, ca.50p.; Unidentified
    Rough notes
  - My Life [Chukchee life history], n.d.; AMs, 9p.; Jochelson, Waldemar, 1855-1937
    Autobiographical account
  - Notes on the Tchi of West Africa, ca.1922; TMs, 121p.; Unidentified
    Ethnographic account of the Twi.
  - The effects of American environment on immigrants and their descendants, n.d. (1910?); TMs, 12p.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Re: physical changes in immigrant populations.
  - Notes of the Uryanskai and Monegher, 1924; AMsS, 4p.; 27 photographs; Bogoras, Waldemar, 1865-1936
    Images include photographs of men and women in native attire, reindeer, and dwellings.
    Microfilmed as: 372.7, reel 3
    Gelatin silver prints
  - Social organization of the Namuavoivoi, n.d.; TMs, 7 p.; Quain, Buell Halvor, 1912-1939
    Comparison of social structure among the Namuavoivoi of Fiji with Polynesian and Maori.
  - The Florida Expedition, n.d.; TMs, 3p.; Hurston, Zora Neale
    Report on work in Florida on Negro folklore.
  - Uganda folklore stories, 1927; AMs, 237p.; Kagwa, Apolo, ed.
    Translated by Ernest B. Kalibala
  - Negro life in a rural community, 1927-1931; TMsS, 165p.; King, Louis E.
    Ethnographic account of rural community in West Virginia.
  - Die Trachten des vorderen Orients, 1933; 60watercolor and pencil sketches; Lange, Gertrud, 1879-
    Illustrations for 52b
  - Die Trachten des Vorderen Orients, 1933; TMs, 196p.; Lange, Gertrud, 1879-
    Thesis submitted under Thilenius at Hamburg. In German.
  - Notes on the political organization and family structure of the Bolum tribe, May 1929; TMs, 21p.; Edel, May M., (May Mandelbaum), 1909-1964
    Paper submitted to Gladys Reichard.
  - Do not retreat..., ca.1927; AMsS, 15p.; Mukasa, Hamu
    Regarding Christianization in Africa (among the Baganda?).
  - Fragments... on observations made in 1929 in the Volga region, TMsS, 13p.; Nadejena, Lydia
    Observations on field work under Waldemar Bogoras.
  - Porto Rican songs, AMsS, 5p.; Roberts, Helen H., (Helen Heffron), 1888-1985
    Muscial notation, with minor comments.
  - Wiicignipi: Chastisement of women, AMsS, 1p.; Seytler, Emil
    Language unidentified
- Achumawi
  - A comparison between the semasiologies of two languages of the so-called Hokan family (Pomo and Achumawi), ca.1931; TMs and AMs, 231L. 10 printed pages; Angulo, Jaime de
    A formal paper with introduction, discussion of morphological elements and phonology of the two languages. Also "Semasiology," a 175-page list of English words according to de Angulo and L. S. Freeland (1930a), with Achumawi and Pomo equivalents. The author concludes that there is little similarity between the two languages, challenging the Kroeber-Dixon use of statistical vocabulary comparisons as a means of determining genetic relationships. List includes names for 86 different birds.
    Freeman and Smith 307
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 9
  - Does Achumawi belong in the Hokan family, TMs and AMS, 20 l.; Angulo, Jaime de
    List of 222 Achumawi-Pomo comparisons. Duplicates part of Semasiology in No. 307.
    Freeman and Smith 309
  - Conversational texts in Achumawi, n.d.; AMs, 72 p.; Angulo, Jaime de
    Includes: sentences in English; Achumawi equivalents; literal English translations; some paradigms and notes on grammatical points; notes on dialectal differences (Atwamdzini, Hammawi, Adzumawi).
    Freeman and Smith 4100
  - Parallel Achumawi and Atsugewi texts, AMs, 11p.; Angulo, Jaime de
    Includes: texts; free English translation; literal translations for some sentences; references to an Achumawi grammar.
    Freeman and Smith 4102
    cf: No. 433
  - Nontechnical description of Achumawi, ca.1931; TMs, 13p.; Angulo, Jaime de
    Includes Angulo's views on the nature of language and linguistic taxonomy. Apparently a portion of a larger work.
    Freeman and Smith 310
  - Reminiscences of an Achumawi youth, n.d.; TMs and AMS, 22pp.; Angulo, Jaime de
    An autobiographical text with numbered English translations corresponding to the Achumawi sentences. Dictated by Willard Carmony, an Achumawi.
    Freeman and Smith 4101
  - Appendix of addenda and corrigenda to the grammar of the Achumawi language, 1931-1935; TMs, 67 l.; Freeland, L. S., (Lucy Shepard), 1890-1972
    Thirteen corrections and 57 additions to de Angulo and Freeland (1930b), based on 1931 field work with Hans J. Uldall. Uldall (1935) was apparently once part of this document.
    Freeman and Smith 312
  - Achumawi texts, ca.1931; TMs and AMs, 156 l.; Freeland, L. S., (Lucy Shepard), 1890-1972
    Tales, myths, and song texts, with interlinear and free translations. 4p. brief ceremonial song texts.
    Freeman and Smith 311
  - Pit River word list, 1907; AMS, 3 slips; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    Brief Achumawi word list.
    Freeman and Smith 313
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    Donor, Morris Swadesh, 1946.
- Acoma
  - Songs from Acoma and Santa Ana, AMS, 69 l.; Stirling, Matthew W.
    Texts of 88 songs with interlinear translations, including typed copy of one song arranged in model form. Numbers refer to phonograph records, not in APS Library. English orthography; phonetic emendations by Franz Boas.
    Freeman and Smith 316
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 11
- Aleut
  - Aleut Folklore, ca.1933; TMs Cy, 132 l.; Unidentified
    An ethnography of the Aleut based on study made of the Aleut texts of Vladimir Jochelson, apparently by a student of Boas. Comparative folklore and abstracts of Aleut tales are included.
    Freeman and Smith 322
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 5
  - Aleut texts, 1909-1910; TMs Cy, 906 l.; Jochelson, Vladimir I.
    Attu and Unalaska texts. No translations. Carbon copy (12p.) of 41, 42, 43, has interlinear translation and notes. These were sent to John Harrington, Nov. B, 1941, in Unalaska. Never published.
    Freeman and Smith 323
    Cf. No. 322.
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 7-8
  - Essay on the grammar of the Aleut language, 1930; TMs and AMs, 83 l.; Jochelson, Vladimir I.
    Preface discusses influence of Fr. Veniaminov's grammar; section on phonology; incomplete descriptive grammar. MS. corrections made by Boas. Never published.
    Freeman and Smith 324
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 8
- Algonkian
  - Classification of Algonkin languages, 1935; TMs, 7 l.; Siebert, Frank T. (Frank Thomas), 1912-1998
    Classified list of languages and bands, showing which are extinct and which are extant and approximate number of speakers as of 1935. Attached note of Edward Sapir to Morris Swadesh on revision in classification of Wiyot and Yurok.
    Freeman and Smith 363
    Donor, Morris Swadesh, 1950.
  - Wiyot-Yurok and Algonkian comparisons, 1915; AMS, 3 l.; Speck, Frank Gouldsmith, 1881-1950
    Cognates in Algonkian languages sent by Speck to Edward Sapir to supplement those used in Sapir (1913). Covering note enclosed.
    Freeman and Smith 364
  - Algonkian comparisons, 1940; TMs and AMs, 75 slips; Hockett, Charles Francis
    Illustrations of cognates and sound correspondences in Algonkian.
    Freeman and Smith 354
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel
  - Beothuk-Algonkian comparisons, 1915; AMS, 5 l.; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    Document prepared for Sapir, copied from Rev. John Leigh's transcription of John Peyton's vocabulary. Compares 45 Beothuk items with Montagnais and Penobscot as well as isolated Micmac, Ojibwa, and Abnaki equivalents. English translations given. Copyist felt transcription was inadequate.
    Freeman and Smith 360
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 6
  - Iroquois, Algonquian and Siouan field notes, 1911; AMS, 1 notebook; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    Vocabulary and texts in Seneca (Grand River); Mohawk (Grand River and Caughnawaga); Delaware (Grand River); Abenaki (Pierreville); Malecite (Rivière du Loup); Micmac (Cacouna); Montagnais (Pointe Blanc); Cree (Pointe Blanc); Algonquian; Tutelo (Grand River).
    Freeman and Smith 361
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.1, reel 36
- Alsea
  - Yakonan (Alsea) grammar, 1918; TMs and AMS, 422 l.; Frachtenberg, Leo Joachim, 1883-1930
    Work intended for publication in Handbook of American Indian Languages, but never printed. Based on field work of J. Owen Dorsey (1884-Siletz, Oregon: vocabularies), Livingston Farrand (1900-Siletz reservation) and the author (1910). Table of contents, grammar, and texts with interlinear and free translations and grammatical notes.
    Freeman and Smith 394
    Cf. texts published in Frachtenberg (1920).
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 14
  - Alsea notes, collected... at Siletz Reserve, 1900; AMS, 6 l.; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    Paradigms.
    Freeman and Smith 395
- Apache
  - Apache (Chiricahua, Lipan, and Jicarilla) morphological lexicon, AMS, 112 cards; Unidentified
    Cards arranged in tables; conjugations of all prefixes (aspectual and pronominal) and combinations thereof. Mentions E. Sapir.
    Freeman and Smith 401
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.1, reel 47
  - San Carlos Apache Lexical File, 1920; AMS and printed, ca.400 cards; Goddard, Pliny Earle, 1869-1928
    Words cut from printed text, Creation Myth, in Goddard (1920): 147-155, pasted on cards.
    Freeman and Smith 402
    Printed source, Goddard (1920).
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.7, reel 16
- Arapaho
  - Sapir on Arapaho, 1939; TMs, 8 l.; Hockett, Charles Francis
    List of correspondences.
    Freeman and Smith 403
    Printed (briefer version), Hockett (1946): 943-245.
  - Arapaho texts, 1950; AMS, 98 l.; Salzmann, Zdenek
    Sample of field notes of texts collected at the Wind River Reservation, Wyoming. Includes sample paradigms.
    Freeman and Smith 404
    Printed (nos. 2.1, 2.2, 2.3, 2.4, 2.5, 3.3, 3.2), Salzmann (1958): 151-158, 266-272.
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.7, reel 2
- Assiniboin
  - The creation of a new tribe, 1949; AMS, 5p.; Ahenakew, Edward
    Explanation of creation of Assiniboin tribe, separated from Sioux, given Ahenakew in his youth by his mission superintendent, Rev. John Hines. Battle over girl accounted for end of connection of Red Eagle with other Sioux. Letter of Ahenakew to Paul A. W. Wallace, May 21, 1949, commenting on Rev. Hines' relation to the author.
    Freeman and Smith 418
    Donor, Edward Ahenakew, grantee, 1949.
  - Notes on the Assiniboine (Belknap or Watopahnatu dialect), 1936; TMs Cy, 59 l.; Deloria, Ella Cara
    A sketch of Assiniboin grammar, compared with that of Dakota. Includes Assiniboin text, with literal and free translation and notes. Letter from author to Boas, Jan. 6, 1936, covering the document.
    Freeman and Smith 420
    Cf. Boas and Deloria (1932)
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 33
- Atakapa
  - Atakapa fragments recorded from descendants of speakers, 1934; AMS, 3 l.; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Fragmentary list of Atacapa items with English equivalents. Obtained near Lake Charles, La.
    Freeman and Smith 423
    Donor, Morris Swadesh, 1953.
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, 8; Film 372.7, 5
- Athapaskan
  - Problems in Athapaskan linguistics, n.d.; TMs Cy, 3 l.; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    Sapir seeks more and better field data on all recoverable dialects, emphasizing difficulties in dealing with these languages, particularly because of tones.
    Freeman and Smith 428
    Donor, Morris Swadesh, 1948
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, 13
  - Field notes in California Athabascan languages, 1903-1911; AMS, 4 notebooks; Goddard, Pliny Earle, 1869-1928
    2 notebooks of Kiowa Apache materials (including text, discussion of warfare; list of specimens and cost). 2 notebooks Athapaskan, including Tolowa texts in English translation [see Tolowa in No. [30(Na20f.1)].
    Freeman and Smith 427
    Donor, A. L. Kroeber for the Department of Anthropology, University of California, 1946.
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.1, 42
  - Lexical file Athabascan language, n.d.; AMS, 75 cards; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Stems and paradigms, reference numbers to field notes.
    Freeman and Smith 426
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.6, 2
  - Comparative Na-Dene dictionary, n.d.; AMs, 4 vol. (ca. 500p. each); Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939